<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Sir</title>
        <link>https://www.leewei.co/</link>
        <description>Sir</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 22:32:19 &#43;0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.leewei.co/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.4 - GitLab Respository</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p4/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 22:32:19 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p4/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[In this post, we are going to set up a GitLab server on GCP. We need a git repository for our CI/CD pipeline. You might ask, there is a native GCP service called, Cloud Source Repository, why don't we just use that. Of course we can use that, but Source Repository lacks a lot of features like merge request, UI for code reviewing etc. In addition, we can learn how to set up our own GitLab Server and configure its domain and SSL, how cool is that.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.3 - Running on GKE</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p3/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 08:32:11 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p3/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[On the previous post, we have already build our Docker image and succefully run it on our local computer. Right now, we are going to learn some basic knowledge of Google Kubernetes Engine and how to deploy our service to it.
Kubernetes Kubernetes(k8s) is an open source system for users to manage their containerized applications.
Why do we need Kubernetes? Kubernetes is a system that makes sure our containers are running as we expected.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.2 - API Server &amp; Docker Image</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p2/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 08:32:11 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p2/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[In this part, we will build a RESTful API server and wrap it in Docker. After that, we'll deploy it on GKE and start build our CI/CD pipeline for the whole project.
Import Environment Variables Using environment variables to define our database parameters is a better way. There are several reasons that we should not hard code our parameters:
Security
I have seen a lot of cases that people upload their credentials or their database information to Github.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>DNS(Domain Name System) Overview</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/dns-brief-records/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 10:41:42 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/dns-brief-records/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[This is a summary of DNS related topics that we met in our daily life. Recommend anyone who wants to dive deep in DNS to read the article written by Cloudflare
What is DNS? The Domain Name System(DNS) is a service that translate domain names to IP addresses. So that, we can load resources from web server to our local browser.
How does DNS work? The process of DNS resolution is the following:]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.1 - Simple HTTP Server</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p1/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 16:37:39 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p1/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[This part 1 of building a Go RESTful API. Our final goal is to build up a CI/CD pipeline using the following tech stack. Wish me luck, nothing is easy in the beginning. 😆
* Go * GitLab -&gt; Repository * GitLab -&gt; CI/CD * PostgreSQL -&gt; Cloud SQL * Docker * Kubernetes -&gt; GKE In this part, we're going to set up a simple HTTP server and local PostgreSQL.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>CMU Databases Systems: 06 Hash Tables</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/hash-tables/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 12:24:08 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/hash-tables/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Hash Tables A hash table is an abstract data type that implements arbitrary array that maps keys to values.
 Space complexity: O(N) Operation complexity: Average is O(1), worst case is O(N).  Hash Function A hash function is how to map a large key space into a smaller domain. Need to consider the trade-off between fast execution vs. collision rate.
The fastest hash function is with a constant key, it will always return the same index.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>PostgreSQL: Create Users, Databases and Tables</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/postgre-sql-create-user-db-tables/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 23:58:56 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/postgre-sql-create-user-db-tables/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[In the last post, we set up our PostgreSQL server. Now, we're going to create users, databases and tables.
PostgreSQL Schema Basics What is the definition of Schema in PostgreSQL Before we begin to create and set up the objects in PostgreSQL, we might need to understand the basic concept of schema in PostgreSQL. This article detailed describe the definition of Schema in PostgreSQL.
In a broader view of RDBMS, Schema is generally refered as the definition of tables, columns and other objects that constitute the database.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>CMU Databases Systems: 05 Buffer Pool &amp; Memory Management</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/buffer-pool/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 11:06:48 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/buffer-pool/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Database Storage  Spatial Control  where to write pages on disk keep pages that are often used together physically as close as possible   Temporal Control  when to read pages into memory, when to write pages to disk minimize the number of stalls from having to read data from disk    Locks vs Latches  Locks  Protect the database logical contents (e.g., tuples, tables, databases) from other transactions Held for transaction duration Need to be able to rollback changes   Latches(It is called Mutex or Locks in the Operating System world)  Protects the critical sections of the DBMS’s internal data structures from other threads Held for operation duration Do not need to be able to rollback changes    Buffer Pool Manager Buffer pool (buffer cache) is an array of fixed-size pages.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>CMU Databases Systems: 04 Database Storage(pt.2)</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/database-storage-02/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 22:26:52 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/database-storage-02/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Andy(lecturer) said that in the early 2000s, Google is making tons of money. And one of the reason Google is expanding and scaling so fast is because they are using HBase, which is called &ldquo;BigTable&rdquo; on GCP. Google is absolutely good at large scale database systems, like Spanner, BigQuery etc. A lot of companies are trying to copy the tech stack of Google. Nevertheless, not all the companies that uses Google Cloud Platform are enterprise level companies, most of them don't have the resource like Google to develop applications using large scale databases.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>CMU Databases Systems: 03 Database Storage(pt.1)</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/database-storage-01/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 20:26:07 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/database-storage-01/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Course Outline The main purpose of this course is How to build a software of database management system.
Storage  Volatile Devices: it needs power to keep its data persistent. Non-Volatile Devices: does not need continous power for device to retain its data.  Non-Volatile Memory: a storage device that is almost as fast as DRAM but with the persistence of a disk.
Disk-Oriented DBMS The data in the database files is organized into pages, and the first page is the directory page.]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
