<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sir</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sir</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 09:57:59 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.leewei.co/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PostgreSQL: Server setup on Ubuntu 18.04</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/postgre-sql-set-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 09:57:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/postgre-sql-set-up/</guid>
      <description>Install PostgreSQL Create a file /etc/apt/sources.list.d/pgdg.list and add the following line to that file deb http://apt.postgresql.org/pub/repos/apt/ bionic-pgdg main. We can get the PostgreSQL APT repository from the official website.
$ sudo sh -c &amp;#39;echo &amp;#34;deb http://apt.postgresql.org/pub/repos/apt/ bionic-pgdg main&amp;#34; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/apt/sources.list.d/pgdg.list&amp;#39; Import the repository public key
$ wget --quiet -O - https://www.postgresql.org/media/keys/ACCC4CF8.asc | sudo apt-key add - Update the repository list and install PostgreSQL
$ sudo apt-get update $ sudo apt-get -y install postgresql Check if PostgreSQL is running as expected</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CMU Databases Systems: 01 Relational Model</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/relational-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 17:29:54 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/cmu-15-445/relational-model/</guid>
      <description>I got rejected by CMU last week. Not surprised by the result, because I prepared the application in a short amount of time. Also, I didn&#39;t do well on the online coding test. Although the outcome is quite depressing, I still managed to look on the bright side. &amp;ldquo;There are numerous CMU online courses, why don&#39;t I just take these courses and do the assignments?&amp;rdquo; Plus, thanks to the freaking Corona virus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL/Mariadb Best Practice</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/mysql-mariadb-best-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 14:37:02 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/mysql-mariadb-best-practice/</guid>
      <description>A note for the best practice of MySQL/MariaDB. (To be updated)
Datatype  Use CHAR datatype if the length of the data is fixed. Instead, use VARCHAR to store variable length data. It is slightly more faster to use CHAR over VARCHAR when the data length is fixed. Avoid using BLOB datatype. Store BLOB data might boost up the total size of the database. We can consifer storing these blob data into other servers, and we store the URL link to these blob.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Startup Playbook: a startup framework</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/start-up-playbook-the-idea/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 12:48:19 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/start-up-playbook-the-idea/</guid>
      <description>I found an startup playbook that is created by Sam Altman, former president of Y Combinator. It&#39;s a great website if anyone wants to start their company in the future. Here is the summery of this playbook and some of my thoughts:
The Idea This is the most important part of starting a startup. A startup needs to focus on what it is solving and who needs this product. It&#39;s not like you can think of a idea overnight, I think sometimes a good idea came from stupid, shitty topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Structures: Array &amp; Linked List</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/ds-array-linked-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:27:34 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/ds-array-linked-list/</guid>
      <description>Array Array is a data structure and it is a collection of elements or values. Each elment is identified by an array index/key.
 Advantages  It is very easy to implement. Random access is O(1) if we know the array index or key.   Disadvantages  It is not a dynamic data structure. It would take O(N) if we want to insert or remove an element in the array.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dependency Inversion Principle</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/dependency-inversion-principle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:13:40 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/dependency-inversion-principle/</guid>
      <description>I accidently knew the concept of Dependency Inversion Principle(DIP) when I was developing a project. Its definition:
High level modules should not depend on low level modules; both should depend on abstractions. Abstractions should not depend on details. Details should depend on abstractions.
Confusing, right? The first time I heard of this principle, I thought it was about the organization of directories. 😆
Example 1: without DIP Let&#39;s say we have an application that has the following structure:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Avoid Asking Bad Questions</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/how-to-avoid-asking-bad-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/how-to-avoid-asking-bad-questions/</guid>
      <description>As a customer engineer, I receive all kinds of questions everyday. For me, I also ask a lot of questions to my colleagues. It is normal if we ask someone for help because we don&#39;t know everything. However, it might be frustrating to handle bad questions. Here are some tips on how we avoid asking bad questions:
1. Google it before asking anyone Sometimes the answer to the question is just one click away.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Structures and Algorithms Introduction</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/data-structures-algorithm-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2019/data-structures-algorithm-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Finally got some time to do this. This is the first post of me learning data structures and algorithms online courses. I&#39;ll take down my notes and put it here to share with you guys. Let&#39;s begin!
Introduction Why is data structures and algorithms so important? Why does every student major in computer science related fields needs to take this course?
The answer is because we need to practice Leetcode questions and pass interviews to get a job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://www.leewei.co/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.leewei.co/about/</guid>
      <description>Lee is an outgoing, meticulous, curious person and a team player. After graduating from NTUST, department of Electrical Engineering, he founds himself a spot in the industry of Cloud Services. He is currently a Technical Support Engineer at iKala Interactive Media Inc., with experience of handling customer&#39;s daily questions in Google Cloud Platform(GCP). He works with GCP, Kuberneters, Docker, Linux and Golang in his daily job.
Lee is also passionate about software developing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>