<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>RESTful - Tag - Sir</title>
        <link>https://www.leewei.co/tags/restful/</link>
        <description>RESTful - Tag - Sir</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 08:32:11 &#43;0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.leewei.co/tags/restful/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.3 - Running on GKE</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p3/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 08:32:11 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p3/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[On the previous post, we have already build our Docker image and succefully run it on our local computer. Right now, we are going to learn some basic knowledge of Google Kubernetes Engine and how to deploy our service to it.
Kubernetes Kubernetes(k8s) is an open source system for users to manage their containerized applications.
Why do we need Kubernetes? Kubernetes is a system that makes sure our containers are running as we expected.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.2 - API Server &amp; Docker Image</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p2/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 08:32:11 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p2/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[In this part, we will build a RESTful API server and wrap it in Docker. After that, we'll deploy it on GKE and start build our CI/CD pipeline for the whole project.
Import Environment Variables Using environment variables to define our database parameters is a better way. There are several reasons that we should not hard code our parameters:
Security
I have seen a lot of cases that people upload their credentials or their database information to Github.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Go RESTful API pt.1 - Simple HTTP Server</title>
    <link>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p1/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 16:37:39 &#43;0800</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://www.leewei.co/posts/2020/go-app-from-scratch-p1/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[This part 1 of building a Go RESTful API. Our final goal is to build up a CI/CD pipeline using the following tech stack. Wish me luck, nothing is easy in the beginning. 😆
* Go * GitLab -&gt; Repository * GitLab -&gt; CI/CD * PostgreSQL -&gt; Cloud SQL * Docker * Kubernetes -&gt; GKE In this part, we're going to set up a simple HTTP server and local PostgreSQL.]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
